Pratik Deb

Senior Researcher

Srinagar-Garhwal, Uttarakhand / India | deb.pratik26@gmail.com

Summary

Highly organized, efficient, meticulous and analytical Researcher with more than 3 years of hands-on experience in GIS; spatial data science; climate change impact assessment; land use mapping; hydro-climatology; hillslope hydrology; hydrological instrumentation and modelling and groundwater studies. Experienced in leading and guiding team members in National Level Projects. Contributed as a Senior Researcher in creating GIS and Hydrology based solutions to increase efficiencies in GIS, Remote Sensing, Water Resources; Urban Water Management and Planning Sector.

Work Experience

Hydrological Scientist (Volunteer)

2020-07 - Present

EQORIA Earth Consortium

- Identifying, analyzing and relating Earth Resources.
- Observing, collecting, analyzing and presenting changes of Earth Resources using Geo-Spatial and other remote sensing technologies.
- Achieving the SDGs requires the partnership of governments, private sector, civil society and citizens alike to make sure we leave a better planet for future generations.
- Analysing the present status of water scarcity throughout the World.

Senior Researcher - GIS / Watershed Management

2017-06 - Present

G.B. Pant National Institute of Himalayan Environment

- Quantification of the hydrological processes and establishment of a functional relationship of land use changes and hydrological responses in social scenario.
- Model development for groundwater augmentation through a participatory approach.
- Development and demonstration of functional land use model using optimized hydrological response at sub-watershed level.
- Assessment of seasonal and annual rainfall trend, homogeneity and change point detection through different statistical methods.
- Vegetative growth analysis of different forest species in the Garhwal Himalaya.
- Population and decadal change assessment in Pauri block, Kaljikhal block and Pauri district through spatial-temporal mapping in GIS environment.
- Dissemination an adaptive land use policy and integrated decision support system for water management at the watershed level to professionals working to develop restoration plans.

Student Researcher - GIS / Hydrological Modelling

2015 - 2016

Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur

- Development of different land use map by quantifying its changes.
- Prediction of the associated probability of change for each land use classes.
- Set up, calibration and validation of SWAT for streamflow to evaluate the effects of land use changes during 1987 to 2011.
- Recommendations regarding adaptive land use policy for water resource management.

Education

M.Tech (Land and Water Resources Engineering) 2014 - 2016 Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur

B.Tech (Agricultural Engineering)
North Bengal Agriculture University

2009 - 2013

Core Competencies

Spatial Analysis

Arc GIS Products

Remote Sensing Applications

Hydrological Modelling

Hydrological Instrumentation

Land use Planning

Watershed Management

Spatial Data Science

Sustainability

Research & Development

Software Skills

ERDAS IMAGINE, ENVI 5.1, eCognition, Arc GIS, QGIS, Global Mapper, Geomatica and IDRISI

Tools

Arc Hydro, Topology, GeoHMS, NDNR Hydrology, Spatial Analyst, CDO and LCM

Models

SWAT, SWMM, WEAP, HBV Light, TOPMODEL, GeoHEC-RAS HEC-RAS and Hydromad

Achievment and Awards

- Secured AIR 47 (AG) in GATE 2014.
- Receiving scholarship provided by MHRD India during 2014 2016.
- Awarded as **YOUNG SCIENTIST** by Uttarakhand State Council for Science and Technology.
- Nominated as "**Hydrological Scientist** & **Planetarian Singularity Impact Specialist**" at EQORIA Earth Academy.

Publications

- **Deb, P.** and Mishra, A., 2016, Forest Cover Change Estimation using Remote Sensing and GIS– A Study of the Subarnarekha River Basin, Eastern India. *The Technology, People and Sustainable Development, 2016 (pp. 161-175)*.
- Kumar, S., Deb, P.and Kumar, A., 2017. Terrain Evaluation and Landform Classification to Assess Landscape Ecology of Bacchanshiv Gad, Garhwal Himalayan Region. *Indian* Cartographer, 37, pp.333-346.
- Pramanik, M., Paudel, U., Mondal, B., Chakraborti, S. and **Deb, P.**, 2018. Predicting climate change impacts on the distribution of the threatened Garcinia Indica in the Western Ghats, India. *Climate Risk Management*, 19, pp.94-105.
- **Deb, P.**, Mishra, A. and Tarafdar, S. 2018. Streamflow Response to Land Use-Land Cover Change over the Subarnarekha River Basin, India. *Hydrological Modelling, Water Management and WaterGovernance, Springer: Water Science and Technology Library.*
- **Deb, P.** and Tarafdar, S. 2019. Land use land cover change and trend analysis of rainfall and temperature patterns in mid-Himalayan catchment using remote sensing data. *Advancement in Basic and Applied Sciences, ANCIENT PUBLISHING HOUSE, New Delhi, ISBN:* 978-93-84866-90-7.
- Tarafdar, S., **Deb, P.**, Kumar, A., Pandey, D. and Kumar, D. 2020. Inventory and Mapping of Springs in Headwaters of Paschimi Nayar River, Pauri District. *Technical Report-I, pp. 01-47, G.B. Pant. National Institute of Himalayan Environment (NIHE), Garhwal Regional Center, Srinagar-Garhwal, Uttarakhand 246 174.*
- **Deb, P.**, Mishra, A., Mushikin, I. and Tarafdar, S., 2017, Application of Landsat Time-series Images to Quantifying Land-use Land cover Dynamic Change and its Future Projection. *International Conference on Remote Sensing and GIS for Applications in Geosciences, pp. 138.*

Membership

- EQORIA Earth Citizen
- EQORIA Earth Academy
- IWRA
- NSPE
- ICIMOD-HUC
- AES, IIT Kharagpur

Certification

Application of Geospatial Technology

Cities and Climate Change

Ecosystem Dynamics and Conservation

Statistical Analysis Using R

Introduction to WASH

Disaster Preparedness

Mountain Matters

Address

13/10 Bundh Road, Bidhan Pally, Ward No. 05, Mathabhanga, Cooch Behar, West Bengal, India 736 146

Website

https://www.linkedin.com/in/pratik-deb-m-tech-b88297137/

Created with **TisualCV**